so this video is about unspeakable and
me Ryan teen for five minutes about
medical system unspeakable is a new CBC
show talking about the tainted blood
scandal in the early eighties when aids
was first discovered and nobody kind of
knew anything so I just finished episode
three it's only three episodes in and I
was really young when this happened and
I'm a very personally affecting our
family because my sister had had
open-heart surgery
and we didn't remember if she'd gotten
blood and that's like if even if she had
gotten blood and we still don't even
know it would have the chance of that
blood being tainted it's very small but
it still affects your family the worry
that this could be something that you
got trying to get healthy trying to get
help from the medical system and then
you get a disease that at that time is a
death sentence but this story I just I
have PTSD around medical stuff but I do
watch medical dramas and like wait do
people have PTSD in war actually watch
war dramas but it's because with medical
dramas they solve everything in an hour
and they are they're like house it's
like we're gonna figure out how to solve
this problem for you and it's not the
case in real life so I can watch the
fake version but experiencing the real
version really triggers me and this show
it's definitely because it's real and
it's all of the that happens and so
I have to stay in the lights and keep
going back and forth so hemophiliacs I
don't know what percentage of the
population is haemophiliac but it
definitely affects men more than women I
do believe it's an x-linked trait have
to look it up I forgot to google that
beforehand I think all of them are men
in the show which makes yeah it's
definitely an accident rate I know that
for my genetics and so if it's just like
the perfect storm because which I didn't
know before watching the series that gay
men were more likely to donate than the
rest of the population just based on
their altruism and their the culture of
altruism and so that's like they are
there so there was more tainted blood in
the system and then would have been if
it was just random and then both the
like homophobia and the like pushback
from homophobia also was its own
shitstorm like okay so then make gay men
count don't know we can't ask a man not
to donate so like it was just bad
all-around bad but the CDC CDC the Red
Cross knew at one
that like okay so hemophiliacs don't
just get one treatment of blood first of
all I need it constantly so even if it
was one treatment they've been exposed
many many times but the product they
were using at that time period was like
20,000 people concentrated like they
just put it in a big vat and then you
took some of that so therefore if one
person amongst that they could infect
anyone so something like 50% of the
hemophiliacs were infected during this
time period then they were like well
they're already infected so like let's
just keep giving you time we have all
this tainted blood so why don't we just
keep giving it to them and we only give
the new pure stuff that we've we've heat
treated to people who are recently
diagnosed or have a very minimum form of
hemophilia and they wanted to keep it
around like they had the tainted blood
they're like but it cost money and this
is it just brings up all of my medical
bureaucracy because it's just
one that doesn't even save money because
we're a socialized medical system in
Canada so you have to treat these people
who you've now infected for the rest of
their lives that cost more money but
they're don't look at it like that they
look at it like okay well there's this
product we have we have to use it before
we can kind of get more just everything
one of the fathers or the father he's
involved I don't remember exactly what
his position I was but he has a son with
hemophilia and knows this is going on
because he's involved his work is
involved in this this procedure this
scandal and so he asks if he can give
his blood directly to his son if they
can make his product out of his blood
and they're like nope can't do it like
it's just all the bureaucracy and it's
such an important story it's also like
these things this isn't this is the
hugest scandal that I know of in this in
this way and it existed like each each
episode is their own year so we're like
three years in that this family is known
there's a problem and of course then
there's all the backlash against the
hemophiliacs to like not like my my son
can't play with your son and and how
dare you let him touch apples in the
grocery store because of all the
ignorance like we didn't
and what if it was caused was spread by
saliva or airborne and it's a deadly
scary disease we didn't understand it as
much back then but all of that all of
that can be made better if transparency
transparency of like okay what is the
evidence that it's tainted what is the
evidence it's not tainted what is the
evidence that heat treatment works what
does the evidence that heat treatment
doesn't work this is just gonna go on
and on it's like they get hope and it
gets dropped I probably should not be
watching this but he's also a fuel for
the fire because this is why I want to
create the medical app so things like
this in the future can be handled at the
people level so we can demand action
when we have the knowledge because
people who've dealt with the medical
system on a constant basis already don't
have faith in it we already know things
like this happen we've had things like
this happen to us
where a doctor gives you tells you
something as safe or something's going
to work or some and then you take it and
it has a negative effect and your
research and it shows yes of course that
has that negative effect I need access
to my medical information we need max
access to our populations medical
information voluntary no forced
demanding of people's just it's my rent
it's my video for today that I wanted to
get done by 10:00 I have own
appointments to talk to someone at 10:00
on the phone I see Lisa just watch it
unspeakable and I also highly suggest we
take back our medical systems all right
thanks see you tomorrow